{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of the Board of Control for Cricket in India (BCCI) is located in -",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  Chennai ",
            "optionD": "  Kolkata ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Board of Control for Cricket in India was formed in December 1928 as a society, registered under the Tamil Nadu Societies Registration Act. It is a consortium of state cricket associations and the state associations select their representatives who in turn elect the BCCI Chief. Its headquarters are in Wankhede Stadium, Mumbai. ",
            "keyString": "783125s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India became a member in 2016 -",
            "optionA": "  Non - Proliferation Treaty ",
            "optionB": "  Missile Technology Control Regime ",
            "optionC": "  Nuclear Suppliers Group ",
            "optionD": "  Wassenaar Arrangement ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia formally applied for membership to the Missile Technology Control Regime in June 2015, with active support from Russia, France and the United States, and officially became a member on 27 June 2016 with the consensus of the 34 member nations. ",
            "keyString": "783154s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Seventeenth conference of NAM was held at -",
            "optionA": "  Cairo ",
            "optionB": "  Porlamar ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Lusaka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Seventeenth conference of NAM was held at Porlamar. ",
            "keyString": "783167s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following cities hosted the Tenth Ministerial Conference of World Trade Organization during December 2015?",
            "optionA": "  Geneva ",
            "optionB": "  Manila ",
            "optionC": "  Helsinki ",
            "optionD": "  Nairobi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe WTO's 10th Ministerial Conference was held in Nairobi, Kenya, from 15 to 19 December 2015.",
            "keyString": "783178s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the country is not a member of SAARC?",
            "optionA": "  Nepal ",
            "optionB": "  Maldives ",
            "optionC": "  China ",
            "optionD": "  Afghanistan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the members of the SAARC are : Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Nepal, Maldives, Pakistan and Sri Lanka. ",
            "keyString": "783188s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Economic and Social Commission for Asia and Pacific (ESCAP) is located at -",
            "optionA": "  Manila ",
            "optionB": "  Singapore ",
            "optionC": "  Kuala Lumpur ",
            "optionD": "  Bangkok ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEstablished in 1947 with its headquarters in Bangkok, Thailand, The Economic and Social Commission for Asia and Pacific (ESCAP) serves as the highest intergovernmental regional platform to promote cooperation among member States for creating a more interconnected region working to achieve inclusive and sustainable economic and social development. ",
            "keyString": "817548s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vietnam joined the UN in the year -",
            "optionA": "  1977 ",
            "optionB": "  1970 ",
            "optionC": "  1976 ",
            "optionD": "  1974 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVietnam became a UN member in 1977. ",
            "keyString": "817576s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The International Court of Justice is located at -",
            "optionA": "  Geneva ",
            "optionB": "  Hague ",
            "optionC": "  Amsterdam ",
            "optionD": "  Vienna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe International Court of Justice, also known as the World Court, is the main judicial organ of the UN. It was established in June 1945 by the Charter of the United Nations and began work in April 1946. The seat of the Court is at the Peace Palace in The Hague (Netherlands).",
            "keyString": "817588s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following international organisations has started the scheme 'Partnership for Peace' for a group of nations?",
            "optionA": "  Organisation of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) ",
            "optionB": "  Economic and Social Commission for Asia and Pacific (ESCAP) ",
            "optionC": "  North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) ",
            "optionD": "  Organisations of African Unity (OAU) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNATO constitutes 28 member states across North America and Europe. The Partnership for Peace (PfP) is a programme of practical bilateral cooperation between individual Euro - Atlantic partner countries and NATO.",
            "keyString": "817599s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pairs of country and the purpose for which UN Peace Keeping Force is maintained is correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Cyprus - to maintain peace between the two dominant ethnic groups in the country ",
            "optionB": "  Mozambique - To supervise a referendum ",
            "optionC": "  El Salvador - to deliver humanitarian aid ",
            "optionD": "  Lebanon - For supervising a 1992 accord ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCyprus - to maintain peace between the two dominant ethnic groups in the country. ",
            "keyString": "817610s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the UN, how many territories were placed under the trusteeship system?",
            "optionA": "  11 ",
            "optionB": "  12 ",
            "optionC": "  13 ",
            "optionD": "  15 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the early years of the United Nations, 11 Territories were placed under the International Trusteeship System. All 11 Territories have either become independent States or have voluntarily joined neighbouring independent countries. ",
            "keyString": "850584s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many members are their in the G-20 group?",
            "optionA": "  20 ",
            "optionB": "  8 ",
            "optionC": "  12 ",
            "optionD": "  16 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs of 2020 there are 20 members of the group : Argentina, Australia, Brazil, Canada, China, the European Union, France, Germany, India, Indonesia, Italy, Japan, Mexico, Russia, Saudi Arabia, South Africa, South Korea, Turkey, United Kingdom, and United States. ",
            "keyString": "850615s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many member countries were founder of the Southern African Development Community?",
            "optionA": "  9 ",
            "optionB": "  8 ",
            "optionC": "  7 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSouthern African Development Community (SADC) was established in April 1980 by governments of the nine Southern African countries of Angola, Botswana, Lesotho, Malawi, Mozambique, Swaziland, Tanzania, Zambia and Zimbabwe. ",
            "keyString": "850628s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many organs are there in UNO?",
            "optionA": "  3 ",
            "optionB": "  6 ",
            "optionC": "  5 ",
            "optionD": "  4 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe United Nations Organisation (UNO) has six main organs. ",
            "keyString": "850639s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Original member states in Bank of Central African States -",
            "optionA": "  5 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  3 ",
            "optionD": "  2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe five original members in Bank of Central African States are Cameroon, Central African Republic, Chad, Republic of the Congo and Gabon. ",
            "keyString": "850649s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian Institute of Remote sensing is located at -",
            "optionA": "  Bengaluru ",
            "optionB": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionC": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "optionD": "  Dehradun ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Institute of Remote sensing is located at Dehradun. ",
            "keyString": "883404s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The latest addition to the list of UNESCO's world heritage sites in India among the following is -",
            "optionA": "  Qutub Minar ",
            "optionB": "  Humayun Tomb  ",
            "optionC": "  Khajuraho Temple ",
            "optionD": "  Red Fort ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe latest addition to the list of UNESCO's world heritage sites in India among the following is Red Fort. ",
            "keyString": "883431s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Official language of Bank of Central African States -",
            "optionA": "  English ",
            "optionB": "  Hindi ",
            "optionC": "  German ",
            "optionD": "  French ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOfficial language of Bank of Central African States is French. ",
            "keyString": "883445s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "National Institute of Nutrition is a institute located in the State of :",
            "optionA": "  Telangana ",
            "optionB": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Institute of Nutrition is a institute located in the State of Telangana. ",
            "keyString": "883456s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "P-5 is a group of -",
            "optionA": "  highly developed countries ",
            "optionB": "  highly populous countries ",
            "optionC": "  permanent members of the Security Council ",
            "optionD": "  established nuclear powers ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Security Council has five permanent members - China, France, Russia, the United Kingdom, and the United States - collectively known as the P-5.",
            "keyString": "883471s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "SAARC is observing a decade (1991 - 2000) of which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Girl child ",
            "optionB": "  Literacy ",
            "optionC": "  Health services to rural poor ",
            "optionD": "  Shelter for all ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSAARC is observing a decade (1991 - 2000) of girl child. ",
            "keyString": "917451s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of Food and Agriculture Organisation is in -",
            "optionA": "  Washington ",
            "optionB": "  Paris ",
            "optionC": "  Madrid ",
            "optionD": "  Rome ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Food and Agriculture Organisation headquarters is located in the city centre of Rome, near the Circo Massimo and close to the Colosseum.",
            "keyString": "917480s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following countries is not a member of Group 15 developing countries?",
            "optionA": "  Mexico ",
            "optionB": "  Malaysia ",
            "optionC": "  Brazil ",
            "optionD": "  Bolivia ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBolivia is not a member of Group 15 developing countries. ",
            "keyString": "917492s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not related to disarmament?",
            "optionA": "  SALT ",
            "optionB": "  NPT ",
            "optionC": "  CTBT ",
            "optionD": "  NATO ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNATO stands for The North Atlantic Treaty Organisation. It was established in the year 1949. Its headquarter is located in Brussels, Belgium. Unlike NPT, SALT, and CTBT, NATO is not related to disarmament.",
            "keyString": "917504s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following describe correctly the Group of Seven Countries (G-7)?",
            "optionA": "  They are developing countries. ",
            "optionB": "  They are industrialised countries. ",
            "optionC": "  They are holding Atomic Bomb technology. ",
            "optionD": "  They are countries who can launch their own satellites. ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Group of seven is a group consisting of Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, the United Kingdom and the United States. These countries, with the 7 largest advanced economies in the world, represent more than 62% of the global net wealth. They are industrialised economies.",
            "keyString": "917515s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of UNHCR is located at -",
            "optionA": "  New York ",
            "optionB": "  Rome ",
            "optionC": "  Geneva ",
            "optionD": "  London ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) is a UN agency mandated to aid and protect refugees, forcibly displaced communities, and stateless people, and to assist in their voluntary repatriation, local integration or resettlement to a third country. It is headquartered in Geneva, Switzerland, with over 17300 staff working in 135 countries. ",
            "keyString": "950623s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a military alliance?",
            "optionA": "  NATO ",
            "optionB": "  NAFTA ",
            "optionC": "  EEC ",
            "optionD": "  ASEAN ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe North Atlantic Treaty Organization was created in 1949 by the United States, Canada, and several Western European nations to provide collective security against the Soviet Union. NATO was the first peacetime military alliance the United States entered into outside of the Western Hemisphere. ",
            "keyString": "950651s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of International Labour Organisation is at -",
            "optionA": "  Paris ",
            "optionB": "  New York ",
            "optionC": "  Hague ",
            "optionD": "  Geneva ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe International Labour Organisation is headquartered in Geneva, Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "950663s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The UNO was founded at -",
            "optionA": "  Moscow ",
            "optionB": "  London ",
            "optionC": "  Paris ",
            "optionD": "  San Francisco ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe UNO was founded on 24 October 1945, San Francisco, California, United States.",
            "keyString": "950674s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first General Secretary of UNO was -",
            "optionA": "  Dag Hamarskjoeld ",
            "optionB": "  U. Thant ",
            "optionC": "  Trygve Lie ",
            "optionD": "  Kurt Waldheim ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrygve Lie, in full Trygve Halvdan Lie was a Norwegian politician and diplomat, the first secretary of the United Nations (1946\u201352), who resigned largely because of the Soviet Union's resentment of his support of UN military intervention in the Korean War. ",
            "keyString": "950685s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Association of South East Asian Nations (ASEAN) is a group of 10 South Asian nations which came into existence after . . . . . . . . . declaration.",
            "optionA": "  Vienna ",
            "optionB": "  Kyoto ",
            "optionC": "  Bangkok ",
            "optionD": "  Singapore ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "984384s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of the Commonwealth of Independent States (CIS), formed out of erst while USSR, is at :",
            "optionA": "  Kistiner in Maldovia ",
            "optionB": "  Kiev in Ukraine ",
            "optionC": "  Moscow in Russia ",
            "optionD": "  Minsk in Belarus ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Commonwealth of Independent States has its headquarters at Minsk, Belarus. ",
            "keyString": "984413s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is 195th member of UNESCO?",
            "optionA": "  Palestine ",
            "optionB": "  Kazakhstan ",
            "optionC": "  Croatia ",
            "optionD": "  South Sudan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter completing procedures for the ratification UNESCO's Constitution on 23 November 2011, Palestine entry as a Member State brought the number of UNESCO's Member States to 195. ",
            "keyString": "984426s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "National Dairy Research Institute is located at :",
            "optionA": "  Ludhiana ",
            "optionB": "  Karnal ",
            "optionC": "  Pantnagar ",
            "optionD": "  Hyderabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe National Dairy Research Institute (NDRI), located in Karnal (Haryana) is a premier research organisation under the aegis of Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR).",
            "keyString": "984439s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In January 2018, 'Friends of MP Conclave' was held in which city?",
            "optionA": "  Bhopal ",
            "optionB": "  Jabalpur ",
            "optionC": "  Indore ",
            "optionD": "  Gwalior ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernment of Madhya Pradesh organised 'Friends of Madhya Pradesh Conclave', at Hotel Marriott, Indore from 3rd to 4th January 2018.",
            "keyString": "984450s32m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The World Trade Organization (WTO) came into effect in -",
            "optionA": "  1990 ",
            "optionB": "  1993 ",
            "optionC": "  1995 ",
            "optionD": "  1997 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe World Trade Organization came into being in 1995. One of the youngest of the international organizations, the WTO is the successor to the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) established in the wake of the Second World War. ",
            "keyString": "17399s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "WTO came into existence in the year - ",
            "optionA": "  1977 ",
            "optionB": "  1985 ",
            "optionC": "  1995 ",
            "optionD": "  1950 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "17428s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did Economic Community of Central African States came into existence?",
            "optionA": "  1984 ",
            "optionB": "  1983 ",
            "optionC": "  1982 ",
            "optionD": "  1981 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEconomic Community of Central African States (ECCAS) was established on 18 October 1983. ",
            "keyString": "17441s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was Niger Basin Authority established?",
            "optionA": "  1983 ",
            "optionB": "  1981 ",
            "optionC": "  1980 ",
            "optionD": "  1982 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1980, the Niger Basin Authority was created with the mandate of speeding up interstate cooperation in the development of the basin resources. ",
            "keyString": "17452s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the Montreal protocol assigned to reduce production of Chlorofluorocarbons?",
            "optionA": "  2001 ",
            "optionB": "  1980 ",
            "optionC": "  1987 ",
            "optionD": "  1994 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Montreal Protocol on Substances that Deplete the Ozone Layer (the Montreal Protocol) is an international agreement made in 1987. ",
            "keyString": "17463s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries is located in -",
            "optionA": "  Vienna  ",
            "optionB": "  Abu Dhabi ",
            "optionC": "  Kuwait ",
            "optionD": "  Riyadh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe OPEC Secretariat is the executive organ of the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC). Located in Vienna, it also functions as the headquarters of the organization. ",
            "keyString": "51248s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Doctors Without Borders (Medecins Sans Frontiers), often in the news, is",
            "optionA": "  A division of World Health Organization  ",
            "optionB": "  A non - governmental international organization ",
            "optionC": "  An inter - governmental agency sponsored by European Union ",
            "optionD": "  A specialized agency of the United Nations ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMedecins Sans Frontiers sometimes rendered in English as Doctors Without Borders, is an international humanitarian medical non - governmental organisation (NGO) of French origin best known for its projects in conflict zones and in countries affected by endemic diseases. ",
            "keyString": "51277s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tuvalu has become a point of discussion. Why?",
            "optionA": "  New innovative technology to meet global warming. ",
            "optionB": "  A country under threat of submergence due to ice melting and sea level rise. ",
            "optionC": "  Potato plant that could grow in high altitude. ",
            "optionD": "  Place in equatorial Africa, where snow is found. ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTuvalu is the world's fourth smallest country, the archipelago of six coral atolls and three islands covers an area of just 26 km2. The existence of the low - lying islands is threatened by rising sea levels caused by global warming. ",
            "keyString": "51290s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did World Health Organization (WHO) come into force?",
            "optionA": "  6th April, 1948 ",
            "optionB": "  7th April, 1948 ",
            "optionC": "  10th April, 1948 ",
            "optionD": "  26th April, 1948 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWHO's Constitution came into force on 7 April 1948. ",
            "keyString": "51301s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When and where was the summit between US President Donald Trump and North Korea leader Kim Jong-un held?",
            "optionA": "  12 June 2018 in Singapore ",
            "optionB": "  7 June 2018 in Manila ",
            "optionC": "  15 June 2018 in Hong Kong ",
            "optionD": "  10 June 2018 in  Seol ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe summit between US President Donald Trump and North Korea leader Kim Jong-Un was held in Singapore on 12 June 2018. ",
            "keyString": "51311s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On 22nd March 2018 who unveiled the book, Neel Ke Dhabbe on the occasion of 106th Bihar Day in Patna?",
            "optionA": "  Vice President Shri Venkaiah Naidu ",
            "optionB": "  Prime Minister Shri Narendra Modi ",
            "optionC": "  Home Minister Shri Rajnath Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Speaker Smt. Sumitra Mahajan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Vice President of India Shri Venkaiah Naidu unveiled the book, Neel Ke Dhabbe on the occasion of 106th Bihar Day in Patna on 22nd March 2018. ",
            "keyString": "85895s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the official language of Southern African Development Community :",
            "optionA": "  English, French ",
            "optionB": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionC": "  German ",
            "optionD": "  A and B ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Southern African Development Community operates a trilingual policy that recognises English, French and Portuguese as its official languages. ",
            "keyString": "85930s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following countries held 11th World Hindi Conference in August 2018?",
            "optionA": "  Suva, Fiji ",
            "optionB": "  Port of Spain, Trinidad and Tobago ",
            "optionC": "  Johannesburg, South Africa ",
            "optionD": "  Port Louis, Mauritius ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 11th World Hindi Conference (WHC) is being organized from 18 - 20 August 2018 in Mauritius by the Ministry of External Affairs, Government of India in association with the Government of Mauritius. ",
            "keyString": "85950s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The office of the UN General Assembly is in :",
            "optionA": "  Vienna ",
            "optionB": "  Paris ",
            "optionC": "  New York ",
            "optionD": "  Zurich ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe General debate is held in the General Assembly Hall at the United Nations headquarters in New York. ",
            "keyString": "85964s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the headquarters of WTO?",
            "optionA": "  Vienna ",
            "optionB": "  Paris ",
            "optionC": "  Bern ",
            "optionD": "  Geneva ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of WTO is in Geneva, Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "85977s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The year 1995 is the Golden Jubilee year of which of the following international organisations?",
            "optionA": "  UNO ",
            "optionB": "  NAM ",
            "optionC": "  GATT (now WTO) ",
            "optionD": "  ASEAN ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe year 1995 is the Golden Jubilee year of United Nations Organisation (UNO). ",
            "keyString": "130427s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The United Nations Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD) is located at which of the following places?",
            "optionA": "  Geneva ",
            "optionB": "  Rome ",
            "optionC": "  Paris ",
            "optionD": "  Vienna ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnited Nations Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD) headquarters are located in Geneva, Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "130460s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amnesty International is an organisation associated with which of the following fields?",
            "optionA": "  Protection of cruelty to animals ",
            "optionB": "  Environment protection ",
            "optionC": "  Protection of human rights ",
            "optionD": "  Protection of historic monuments ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmnesty International (AI), international nongovernmental organization (NGO) founded in London on 28 May 1961, that seeks to publicize violations by governments and other entities of rights recognized in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights (1948), especially freedom of speech and of conscience and the right against torture.",
            "keyString": "130473s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Halifax summit was that of -",
            "optionA": "  G-7 countries ",
            "optionB": "  Leaders of the NAM ",
            "optionC": "  Countries in favour of a common currency for Europe ",
            "optionD": "  Palestinian and Israeli leaders ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 21st G7 summit was held on June 15 - 17, 1995 in Halifax, Nova Scotia, Canada. ",
            "keyString": "130485s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The office of the UN General Assembly is in -",
            "optionA": "  Vienna ",
            "optionB": "  New York ",
            "optionC": "  Paris ",
            "optionD": "  Zurich ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe General debate is held in the General Assembly Hall at the United Nations headquarters in New York. ",
            "keyString": "130496s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India was elected as a President of General Assembly of the United Nations in 1953. Who occupied the office on behalf of India?",
            "optionA": "  S. Radha Krishnan ",
            "optionB": "  Gopalswamy Iyyengar ",
            "optionC": "  V. K. Krishna Menon ",
            "optionD": "  Vijaya Lakshmi Pandit ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1953, the chief delegate of India at the time, Vijaya Lakshmi Pandit was elected the first woman President of the UN General Assembly. ",
            "keyString": "178282s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "United Nations adapted a Charter of Economic Rights in the year -",
            "optionA": "  1969 ",
            "optionB": "  1974 ",
            "optionC": "  1956 ",
            "optionD": "  1964 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe General Assembly adopted \"Charter of Economic Rights and Duties of States\" on 12 December 1974. ",
            "keyString": "178315s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which organ of the United Nations has ceased to be operational?",
            "optionA": "  Economic and Social Council ",
            "optionB": "  International Court of Justice ",
            "optionC": "  Trusteeship Council ",
            "optionD": "  Secretariat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "178333s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The United Nations is considered as a universal organisation. Which organ of the united nations fully represents the fact?",
            "optionA": "  The Economic and Social Council ",
            "optionB": "  The Security Council ",
            "optionC": "  The Secretariat ",
            "optionD": "  The General Assembly ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll 193 Member States of the UN are represented in the General Assembly, making it the only UN body with universal representation. ",
            "keyString": "178346s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of the International Tropical Timber Organization is located at -",
            "optionA": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Yokohama ",
            "optionC": "  Madrid ",
            "optionD": "  Jakarta ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of the International Tropical Timber Organization is located in Yokohama, Japan. ",
            "keyString": "178358s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In October 2014, India has been re-elected for three years as a member to -",
            "optionA": "  The UN Security Council ",
            "optionB": "  The UN General Assembly ",
            "optionC": "  The UN Economic and Social Council (ECOSOC) ",
            "optionD": "  The World Bank ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn October 2014, India was re-elected for three years as a member to UN Economic and Social Council (ECOSOC). ",
            "keyString": "249238s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following statements about United Nations organs is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Decisions of the General Assembly are blinding on all members. ",
            "optionB": "  The term of the non-permanent members of the Security Council is for three years. ",
            "optionC": "  International Court of Justice has 20 Judges elected for a period of five years. ",
            "optionD": "  The Trusteeship Council has been suspended since 1 November 1994. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Trusteeship Council suspended its operations on 1 November 1994, a month after the independence of Palau, the last remaining United Nations trust territory. ",
            "keyString": "249267s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which institute has been awarded the 2018 National Intellectual Property Award in the category Top R & D Institution/Organization for Patents and Commercialization?",
            "optionA": "  The Council of Scientific and Industrial Research ",
            "optionB": "  The Indian Space Research Organization ",
            "optionC": "  The Bhabha Atomic Research Centre ",
            "optionD": "  The Defence Research and Development Organisation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR) was awarded the National Intellectual Property (IP) Award 2018 in the category 'Top R&D Institution/Organisation for Patents and Commercialisation'. ",
            "keyString": "249279s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarter of the International Court of Justice is at :",
            "optionA": "  Geneva ",
            "optionB": "  Hague ",
            "optionC": "  Rome ",
            "optionD": "  Vienna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarter of the International Court of Justice is at Hague. ",
            "keyString": "249290s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not true for SAFTA (South Asian Free Trade Area)?",
            "optionA": "  It is a step towards a South Asian customs union and common market. ",
            "optionB": "  The agreement came into effect in 2006. ",
            "optionC": "  The SAFTA is a trade liberalisation regime. ",
            "optionD": "  The SAFTA agreement takes precedence over any other agreement a member country may have with states outside SAFT",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"The SAFTA agreement takes precedence over any other agreement a member country may have with states outside SAFTA\" is an incorrect statement. ",
            "keyString": "249301s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not a member of MERCOSUR (Southern Common Market)?",
            "optionA": "  Argentina ",
            "optionB": "  Paraguay ",
            "optionC": "  Uruguay ",
            "optionD": "  Chile ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMERCOSUR (Southern Common Market) full - time members are Argentina, Brazil, Paraguay, and Uruguay. ",
            "keyString": "281329s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the headquarters of Pan American Health Organization?",
            "optionA": "  Washington DC ",
            "optionB": "  Ottawa ",
            "optionC": "  New York ",
            "optionD": "  Mexico ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of Pan American Health Organization is in Washington DC, United States. ",
            "keyString": "281354s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is not a Bretton Woods Institution?",
            "optionA": "  IMF ",
            "optionB": "  OECD ",
            "optionC": "  None ",
            "optionD": "  World Bank ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bretton Woods Institutions are the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund (IMF). ",
            "keyString": "281367s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was West African Development Bank formed?",
            "optionA": "  November, 1978 ",
            "optionB": "  November, 1979 ",
            "optionC": "  November, 1973 ",
            "optionD": "  November, 1976 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe West African Development Bank (BOAD) is the common development finance institution of the member countries of the West African Monetary Union (WAMU). It was established by an Agreement signed on 14 November 1973, and became operational in 1976.",
            "keyString": "281378s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the full form of NATO?",
            "optionA": "  North Atlantic Treaty Organization ",
            "optionB": "  North Asian Treaty Organization ",
            "optionC": "  North American Treaty Organization ",
            "optionD": "  North African Treaty Organization ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNATO stands for North Atlantic Treaty Organization. ",
            "keyString": "281389s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The oldest mutual fund in India is the - ",
            "optionA": "  SBI Mutual Fund ",
            "optionB": "  BOB Mutual Fund ",
            "optionC": "  PNB Mutual Fund ",
            "optionD": "  UTI Mutual Fund ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmong 45 odd mutual fund house in India, UTI Asset Management Company Ltd. (UTI AMC) is one of the oldest and most reputed names. ",
            "keyString": "315317s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "19th SAARC Summit was planned to be held in November 2016 but it got postponed. Which country was its host?",
            "optionA": "  Nepal ",
            "optionB": "  Bhutan ",
            "optionC": "  India ",
            "optionD": "  Pakistan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPakistan was the host of 19th SAARC Summit that was planned to be held in November 2016 but got postponed. ",
            "keyString": "315345s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which country became seventh member of SASEC on 31 March 2017?",
            "optionA": "  Myanmar ",
            "optionB": "  Bhutan ",
            "optionC": "  Nepal ",
            "optionD": "  Maldives ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMyanmar on 31 March 2017 became the seventh member of the South Asia Sub - regional Economic Cooperation (SASEC) Program. ",
            "keyString": "315359s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the 14th Asia Security Summit (Shangri - La Dialogue) held in May 2015?",
            "optionA": "  Beijing ",
            "optionB": "  Bangkok ",
            "optionC": "  Jakarta ",
            "optionD": "  Singapore ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 14th Asia - Pacific Security Summit, also known as the IISS Shangri - La Dialogue, will be held in Singapore from 29 - 31 May 2015. ",
            "keyString": "315370s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the official language of Central Bank of West African Bank?",
            "optionA": "  French  ",
            "optionB": "  Arabic ",
            "optionC": "  English ",
            "optionD": "  Hindi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe official language of Central Bank of West African Bank is Arabic. ",
            "keyString": "315382s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Security Council of the UN comprises of 10 non - permanent members and their tenure is . . . . . . . . . .",
            "optionA": "  5 years ",
            "optionB": "  4 years ",
            "optionC": "  3 years ",
            "optionD": "  2 years ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ten elected or non - permanent members have a tenure of two years. ",
            "keyString": "349154s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following countries:\n1. Australia\n2. Canada\n3. China\n4. India\n5. Japan\n6. USA\nWhich of the above are among the 'free - trade partners' of ASEAN?",
            "optionA": "  1, 2, 4 and 5 ",
            "optionB": "  3, 4, 5 and 6 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 3, 4 and 5 ",
            "optionD": "  2, 3, 4 and 6 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tASEAN has five free trade agreements (FTAs) with six Dialogue Partners, namely China, Japan, Republic of Korea, India, Australia and New Zealand. ",
            "keyString": "349183s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was Lake Chad Basin Commission founded :",
            "optionA": "  22nd May 1964 ",
            "optionB": "  24th May 1964 ",
            "optionC": "  28th May 1964 ",
            "optionD": "  29th May 1964 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLake Chad Basin Commission was founded on 22nd May 1964. ",
            "keyString": "349199s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements regarding Indian Ocean Rim Association :\n1. The 13th Council of Ministers Meeting of the Association was held in November 2013 in Perth.\n2. India was elected Chair of the Association from 2013 to 2015.\n3. There are twenty member nations in the Association.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the statements about Indian Ocean Rim Association are correct. ",
            "keyString": "349211s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements :\n1. New Development Bank has been set up by APEC.\n2. The headquarters of New Development Bank is in Shanghai.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe New Development Bank (NDB), formerly referred to as the BRICS Development Bank, is a multilateral development bank established by the BRICS states (Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa). ",
            "keyString": "349224s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The WTO came into being on -",
            "optionA": "  1st April 1995 ",
            "optionB": "  1st April 1994 ",
            "optionC": "  1st January 1995 ",
            "optionD": "  1st January 1996 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe WTO began life on 1st January 1995, but its trading system is half a century older. ",
            "keyString": "381407s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are UNESCO recognized world heritage sites?\n1. Caves of Ajanta\n2. Temples and caves at Ellora\n3. Mandapas of Mahabalipuram\n4. Caves of Kanheri\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
            "optionA": "  1 and 4 only ",
            "optionB": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  2, 3 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCaves of Kanheri is not in the list of UNESCO recognized world heritage sites. ",
            "keyString": "381431s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements about IAEA -\n1. It was set up as the world's Atoms for Peace organization in 1957.\n2. The IAEA Secretariat is headquartered at the Vienna International Centre in Vienna, Austria.\n3. In terms of its Statue, the IAEA reports annually to the UN General Assembly.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 only ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  3 only ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe International Atomic Energy Agency is an international organization that seeks to promote the peaceful use of nuclear energy, and to inhibit its use for any military purpose, including nuclear weapons. The IAEA was established as an autonomous organisation on 29 July 1957. ",
            "keyString": "381447s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 3rd meeting of the SAARC Culture Ministers, convened in New Delhi on 25 September 2014, unanimously resolved.\n1. To declare 2015 - 16 as the SAARC year of Cultural Heritage.\n2. That Bamiyan will be the SAARC cultural capital for 2015 - 16.\n3. To promote SAARC culture online by launching a dedicated SAARC website on culture, with emphasis on digitization of rare manuscripts, rare books and other articles of intangible cultural value.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  2 only ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe SAARC Culture Ministers appraised the meeting on national initiatives on conservation, preservation and promotion of cultural heritage, commended the work done by the SAARC Cultural Centre in Colombo in implementation of the SAARC agenda for culture and recognising the financing requirements of cultural development programs, proposed a joint meeting of SAARC Culture Ministers with SAARC Ministers of Finance. ",
            "keyString": "381461s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following nations were recently suspended with regard to the voting rights by the UNESCO for not paying their dues to it?\n1. United States of America\n2. Israel\n3. Iran\n4. Iraq\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.\n",
            "optionA": "  1, 2, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 only ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  3 and 4 only ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo years after they stopped paying their dues to UNESCO, the United States and Israel lost UNESCO voting rights. ",
            "keyString": "381474s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did the UN General Assembly establish UN Industrial Development Organization?",
            "optionA": "  1968 ",
            "optionB": "  1966 ",
            "optionC": "  1967 ",
            "optionD": "  1965 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 17 November 1966, the UN General Assembly passes Resolution 2152 establishing the UN Industrial Development Organization as an autonomous body within the United Nations. Its mission was to promote and accelerate the industrialization of developing countries. ",
            "keyString": "413601s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was Central Bank of West African States formed?",
            "optionA": "  1964 ",
            "optionB": "  1963 ",
            "optionC": "  1962 ",
            "optionD": "  1965 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCentral Bank of West African States was formed on 12 May 1962. ",
            "keyString": "413630s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Atomic Energy Commission was set up in :",
            "optionA": "  1948 ",
            "optionB": "  1950 ",
            "optionC": "  1952 ",
            "optionD": "  1960 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Atomic Energy Commission was first setup in August 1948 in the Department of Scientific Research, which was created a few months earlier in June 1948. ",
            "keyString": "413643s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year United Nations Organization was formed?",
            "optionA": "  1945 ",
            "optionB": "  1947 ",
            "optionC": "  1954 ",
            "optionD": "  1919 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnited Nations Organization was formed on 24 October 1945, San Francisco, California, United States.",
            "keyString": "413653s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The International Court of Justice was established in the year :",
            "optionA": "  1947 ",
            "optionB": "  1945 ",
            "optionC": "  1950 ",
            "optionD": "  1948 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe International Court of Justice, also known as the World Court, is the main judicial organ of the UN. It was established in June 1945 by the Charter of the United Nations and began work in April 1946. ",
            "keyString": "413664s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not associated with the UNO?",
            "optionA": "  ILO ",
            "optionB": "  WHO ",
            "optionC": "  ASEAN ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUNO: United Nations OrganizationILO: International Labour Organization",
            "keyString": "445662s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The chairmanship/presidency of the UN Security Council rotates among the Council Members -",
            "optionA": "  every 6 months ",
            "optionB": "  every 3 months ",
            "optionC": "  every year ",
            "optionD": "  every month ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The presidency of the United Nations Security Council rotates on a monthly basis alphabetically among all of the members based on their English name.",
            "keyString": "445690s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a chief organ of the United Nations Organisation?",
            "optionA": "  International Labour Organisation ",
            "optionB": "  Security Council ",
            "optionC": "  International Court of Justice ",
            "optionD": "  General Assembly ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main organs of the United Nations Organisation are the General Assembly, the Security Council, the Economic and Social Council, the Trusteeship Council, the International Court of Justice, and the UN Secretariat. ",
            "keyString": "445703s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Permanent Secretariat to coordinate the implementation of SAARC programme is located at -",
            "optionA": "  Dhaka ",
            "optionB": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Colombo ",
            "optionD": "  Kathmandu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe SAARC was founded in Dhaka on 8 December 1985. Its secretariat is based in Kathmandu, Nepal. The organization promotes development of economic and regional integration. ",
            "keyString": "445714s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian delegation to the first World Conference on Human Rights was led by -",
            "optionA": "  Dr. Manmohan Singh ",
            "optionB": "  Farooq Abdullah ",
            "optionC": "  Dinesh Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Alam Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDr. Manmohan Singh is the first Indian delegation that attended the first World Conference. The whole conference was on Human Rights. ",
            "keyString": "445725s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the official language of West African Development Bank?",
            "optionA": "  Arabic ",
            "optionB": "  French ",
            "optionC": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionD": "  English ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe official language of West African Development Bank is French. ",
            "keyString": "479020s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In October 2018, India was elected as a member to the United Nations Human Rights Council for a period of - ",
            "optionA": "  Five years ",
            "optionB": "  Four years ",
            "optionC": "  Three years ",
            "optionD": "  Two years ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia was elected to the United Nations top human rights body for a period of three years beginning 1 January, 2019. ",
            "keyString": "479048s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On 2nd June 2015 a Conference on Make in India Indigenisation of currency was organised by the department of Economic Affairs, Ministry of Finance, Government of India. Who inaugurated the Conference?",
            "optionA": "  Governor R. ",
            "optionB": " I. ",
            "optionC": "  Finance Minister ",
            "optionD": "  Prime Minister ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFinance Minister Arun Jaitley inaugurated the conference on 'Make in India - Indigenization of Currency' in New Delhi. He underlined the need for indigenization of paper, ink and security features of Indian currency. In this context, he mentioned the beginning of commercial production of higher denomination of bank note paper at SPM, Hoshangabad. ",
            "keyString": "479061s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 2 + 2 Bilateral Dialogue was held in September 2018 between -",
            "optionA": "  External Affairs and Defence Ministers of India with their US counterparts ",
            "optionB": "  Finance and Defence Ministers of India with their Russian counterparts ",
            "optionC": "  Home and Defence Ministers of India and their counterparts in Pakistan ",
            "optionD": "  External Affairs and Defence Ministers of India with their counterparts in Pakistan ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "479072s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "BRICS leaders signed the agreement to establish a New Development Bank at the summit held in :",
            "optionA": "  New Delhi, India (2012) ",
            "optionB": "  Durban, South Africa (2013) ",
            "optionC": "  Fortaleza, Brazil (2014) ",
            "optionD": "  Ufa, Russia (2015) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAgreement on the New Development Bank was signed during 6th BRICS Summit held in Fortaleza, Brazil (2014). ",
            "keyString": "479083s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the implementing ministry of Jeevan Jyoti Beema Yojana of Government of India?",
            "optionA": "  Health and Family welfare ",
            "optionB": "  Commerce & Industry ",
            "optionC": "  Finance ",
            "optionD": "  Agriculture & Farmers Welfare ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "515208s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The SAARC Secretariat is located at -",
            "optionA": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Colombo ",
            "optionC": "  Kathmandu ",
            "optionD": "  Karachi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe SAARC Secretariat is based in Kathmandu, Nepal. ",
            "keyString": "515236s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The five permanent members of the UN security council are -",
            "optionA": "  USA, China, France, Russia and Canada ",
            "optionB": "  China, France, Russia, UK and USA ",
            "optionC": "  Japan, Germany, Russia, UK and USA ",
            "optionD": "  Germany, China, USA, Russia and UK ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe five permanent members of the UN security council are China, France, Russia, UK and USA. ",
            "keyString": "515249s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following statements is not correct in respect of the South Asian Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC)?",
            "optionA": "  Its headquarters is located in Kathmandu. ",
            "optionB": "  China is the only country with an observer status in SAAR",
            "optionC": " ",
            "optionD": "  The first SAARC Summit was held in Dhaka. ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"China is the only country with an observer status in SAARC\" is an incorrect statement. ",
            "keyString": "515260s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "BRICS Summit 2016 was held in -",
            "optionA": "  Brazil ",
            "optionB": "  China ",
            "optionC": "  India ",
            "optionD": "  South Africa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBRICS Summit 2016 was held from 15 to 16 October 2016 at the Taj Exotica hotel in Benaulim, Goa, India. ",
            "keyString": "515271s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "G-15 is a group of -",
            "optionA": "  developing countries ",
            "optionB": "  non-aligned countries ",
            "optionC": "  developed countries ",
            "optionD": "  companies ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe G-15, a group of 17 developing countries from Asia, Africa and Latin America, was set up to foster cooperation and provide input for other international groups, such as the World Trade Organization and the Group of Seven rich industrialized nations. The G-15 focuses on cooperation among developing countries in the areas of investment, trade, and technology. The membership of the G-15 has expanded to 18 countries, but the name has remained unchanged. ",
            "keyString": "558365s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian Red Cross Society was established in the year -",
            "optionA": "  1932 ",
            "optionB": "  1920 ",
            "optionC": "  1945 ",
            "optionD": "  1890 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Red Cross Society (IRCS) was established in 1920 under the Indian Red Cross Society Act. The act was last amended in 1992 and of rules were formed in 1994. ",
            "keyString": "558394s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "SAARC was founded in -",
            "optionA": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Geneva ",
            "optionC": "  Dhaka ",
            "optionD": "  Thimpu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSAARC was founded in Dhaka, Bangladesh.",
            "keyString": "558408s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which organ of United Nations has ceased to be operational?",
            "optionA": "  Trusteeship Council ",
            "optionB": "  Secretariat ",
            "optionC": "  International Court of Justice ",
            "optionD": "  Economic and Social Council ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Trusteeship Council suspended its operations on 1 November 1994, a month after the independence of Palau, the last remaining United Nations trust territory.",
            "keyString": "558421s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The member countries of NAFTA are -",
            "optionA": "  USA and Canada ",
            "optionB": "  USA, Canada and Mexico ",
            "optionC": "  Canada and Mexico ",
            "optionD": "  USA and Mexico ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe member countries of NAFTA are USA, Canada and Mexico.",
            "keyString": "558432s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is principal organ of the United Nations that as virtually accomplished its object?",
            "optionA": "  The Security Council ",
            "optionB": "  The General Assembly ",
            "optionC": "  The International Court of Justice ",
            "optionD": "  The Trusteeship Council ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "590866s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of the UNESCO is at -",
            "optionA": "  Rome ",
            "optionB": "  Geneva ",
            "optionC": "  New York ",
            "optionD": "  Paris ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUNESCO has 195 Members and 8 Associate Members and is governed by the General Conference and the Executive Board. The Organization has more than50 field offices around the world and its headquarters are located in Paris.",
            "keyString": "590894s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which UN body deals with population problem?",
            "optionA": "  UNFPA ",
            "optionB": "  UNDP ",
            "optionC": "  UNICEF ",
            "optionD": "  UNESCO ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUNFPA is a subsidiary organ of the United Nations General Assembly. It plays a unique role within the United Nations system: to address population and development issues, with an emphasis on reproductive health and gender equality. ",
            "keyString": "590907s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Besides UK, USA, Germany and Japan the G-7 countries includes -",
            "optionA": "  Canada, France and Russia ",
            "optionB": "  Canada, Italy and Netherlands ",
            "optionC": "  France, Netherlands and Russia ",
            "optionD": "  Canada, France and Italy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tG-7 countries consist of the US, UK, France, Germany, Italy, Canada, and Japan.",
            "keyString": "590918s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of World Intellectual Property Organisation (WIPO) is located in -",
            "optionA": "  Paris ",
            "optionB": "  Madrid ",
            "optionC": "  New York ",
            "optionD": "  Geneva ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWIPO is a intergovernmental organization, with its headquarters in Geneva, Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "590929s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Match the United Nations Agency with its headquarters and find the incorrect match?",
            "optionA": "  UNESCO - Paris, France ",
            "optionB": "  UNIDO - Vienna, Austria ",
            "optionC": "  ILO - Geneva, Switzerland ",
            "optionD": "  FAO - Montreal, Canada ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of Food and Agriculture Organization is in Italy, Rome. ",
            "keyString": "629735s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The International Human Rights Convention adopted by the United Nations in 1990 relates to -",
            "optionA": "  disabled ",
            "optionB": "  stateless persons ",
            "optionC": "  migrant workers ",
            "optionD": "  children ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe International Convention on the Protection of the Rights of All Migrant Workers and Members of their Families (ICMW) is a comprehensive international human rights mechanism adopted by the United Nations in 1990 with the purpose of protecting the migrant workers and members of their families. ",
            "keyString": "663593s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the first Indian to be President of UN General Assembly?",
            "optionA": "  Mrs. Vijaya Lakshmi Pandit ",
            "optionB": "  Ramesh Bhandari ",
            "optionC": "  Natwar Singh ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna Menon ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVijaya Lakshmi Pandit (18 August 1900 - 1 December 1990) was an Indian diplomat and politician who was the first female elected to 6th Governor of Maharashtra and 8th President of the United Nations General Assembly. ",
            "keyString": "663622s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many former republics of USSR have become members of the Commonwealth of Independent States?",
            "optionA": "  11 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  12 ",
            "optionD": "  9 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCommonwealth of Independent States (CIS), free association of sovereign states that was formed in 1991 by Russia and 11 other republics that were formerly part of the Soviet Union. ",
            "keyString": "663635s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The five permanent members of UN security council are",
            "optionA": "  Japan, West Germany, USSR, UK and USA ",
            "optionB": "  Canada, China, France, USSR and USA ",
            "optionC": "  Germany, China, USSR, UK and USA ",
            "optionD": "  China, France, USSR, UK and USA ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe permanent members of the United Nations Security Council (also known as the Permanent Five, Big Five, or P5) are the five sovereign states to whom the UN Charter of 1945 grants a permanent seat on the UN Security Council: China, France, Russia, the United Kingdom, and the United States. ",
            "keyString": "663646s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the South Asian Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC) formed?",
            "optionA": "  1985 ",
            "optionB": "  1982 ",
            "optionC": "  1986 ",
            "optionD": "  1987 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe South Asian Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC) was formed on 8 December 1985.",
            "keyString": "663657s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year 'Human Rights Resolution' was adopted by the UN?",
            "optionA": "  1945 ",
            "optionB": "  1946 ",
            "optionC": "  1947 ",
            "optionD": "  1948 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "695794s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Article of the UN Charter established the International Trusteeship System?",
            "optionA": "  78 ",
            "optionB": "  79 ",
            "optionC": "  75 ",
            "optionD": "  74 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 75 The United Nations shall establish under its authority an international trusteeship system for the administration and supervision of such territories as may be placed thereunder by subsequent individual agreements. These territories are hereinafter referred to as trust territories. ",
            "keyString": "695855s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many member countries are there in the Executive Board of UNESCO?",
            "optionA": "  68 ",
            "optionB": "  58 ",
            "optionC": "  28 ",
            "optionD": "  88 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tExecutive Board of UNESCO consists of 58 Member States each with a four - year term of office. ",
            "keyString": "695887s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many countries are represented in Unrepresented Nations and Peoples Organisation?",
            "optionA": "  54 ",
            "optionB": "  53 ",
            "optionC": "  58 ",
            "optionD": "  59 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "695917s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many non - regional members are there in the African Development Bank?",
            "optionA": "  24 ",
            "optionB": "  23 ",
            "optionC": "  26 ",
            "optionD": "  27 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are 26 non - regional members in the African Development Bank. ",
            "keyString": "695936s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The latest official language of the UN is :",
            "optionA": "  Chinese ",
            "optionB": "  Spanish ",
            "optionC": "  Russian ",
            "optionD": "  Arabic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe latest official language of the UN is Arabic. ",
            "keyString": "748242s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the group of countries known as BRICS, S stands for :",
            "optionA": "  Singapore ",
            "optionB": "  Spain  ",
            "optionC": "  South Africa ",
            "optionD": "  South Korea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the group of countries known as BRICS, S stands for South Africa.",
            "keyString": "748273s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Union Cabinet has approved MoU between India and SACEP for cooperation on oil and chemical pollution in the South Asian seas region. What does SACEP stand for?",
            "optionA": "  South Asia Compatibility Environment Programme ",
            "optionB": "  South Asia Cooperative Environment Programme ",
            "optionC": "  South Asia Connectivity Environment Programme ",
            "optionD": "  South Asia Coercive Environment Programme ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSACEP stand for South Asia Cooperative Environment Programme. ",
            "keyString": "748284s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the headquarters of East African Development Bank?",
            "optionA": "  Uganda ",
            "optionB": "  South Africa ",
            "optionC": "  Zambia ",
            "optionD": "  Zimbabwe ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of East African Development Bank is in Kampala, Uganda. ",
            "keyString": "748295s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 10th BRICS Summit 2018 was held in which of the following countries?",
            "optionA": "  Brazil ",
            "optionB": "  South Africa ",
            "optionC": "  Russia ",
            "optionD": "  China ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 10th BRICS Summit 2018 was held in South Africa. ",
            "keyString": "748304s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pair is not correct :",
            "optionA": "  IAEA - New Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  WTO - Geneva ",
            "optionC": "  UPU - Bern ",
            "optionD": "  IMF - Washington ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe IAEA has its headquarters in Vienna, Austria. ",
            "keyString": "781652s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following is the first UN agency to accept Palestine as its full member in October 2011?",
            "optionA": "  UNESCO ",
            "optionB": "  WTO ",
            "optionC": "  WHO ",
            "optionD": "  IMF ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 31 October 2011, following the admission of Palestine to UNESCO, the Minister of Health Fathi Abu Moghli announced that the PLO would also seek membership at the World Health Organization. ",
            "keyString": "781681s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of which one of the following organizations is not in Geneva?",
            "optionA": "  Food and Agriculture Organisation ",
            "optionB": "  World Meteorological Organisation ",
            "optionC": "  World Health Organisation ",
            "optionD": "  World Trade Organisation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of Food and Agriculture Organisation is in Rome, Italy.",
            "keyString": "781694s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "15th Pravasi Bhartiya Diwas in January 2019 will be held in which city?",
            "optionA": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionB": "  Vadodara ",
            "optionC": "  Jaipur ",
            "optionD": "  Pune ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t15th Pravasi Bhartiya Diwas in January 2019 was held in Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "781705s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Doha Development Agenda' sometimes appears :",
            "optionA": "  Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development ",
            "optionB": "  United Conference on Trade and Development ",
            "optionC": "  United Nations Development Programme ",
            "optionD": "  World Trade Organisation ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Doha Development Round or Doha Development Agenda (DDA) is the trade\u200b negotiation round of the World Trade Organization (WTO). ",
            "keyString": "781718s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the headquarters of African Development Bank?",
            "optionA": "  Abidjan ",
            "optionB": "  Niger ",
            "optionC": "  Namibia ",
            "optionD": "  Nigeria ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of African Development Bank is in Abidjan. ",
            "keyString": "814456s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the headquarters of SIDBI located?",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionD": "  Hyderabad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSIDBI is headquartered in Lucknow. ",
            "keyString": "814484s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Thirteenth Pravasi Bhartiya Divas was held on 8th and 9th January 2015 at -",
            "optionA": "  Gandhinagar ",
            "optionB": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Bengaluru ",
            "optionD": "  Indore ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 13th Pravasi Bharatiya Divas was held during 8 - 9 January 2015 at Mahatma Mandir, Gandhinagar, Gujarat.",
            "keyString": "814498s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the headquarters of the United Nations Environment Programme (UNEP)?",
            "optionA": "  Hague ",
            "optionB": "  Nairobi ",
            "optionC": "  New York ",
            "optionD": "  Washington DC ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of the United Nations Environment Programme (UNEP) is in Nairobi, Kenya. ",
            "keyString": "814512s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was the venue of 2nd BRICS Youth Summit of the Ministers, Officials and Youth Delegations?",
            "optionA": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  Shillong ",
            "optionD": "  Guwahati ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The venue of the 2nd BRICS Youth Summit of the Ministers, Officials and Youth Delegations was Guwahati, Assam. ",
            "keyString": "814523s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which one of the following places is the Forest Survey of India (FSI), a national organization engaged in forest cover mapping, forest inventory and training in the field of remote sensing and GIS, located?",
            "optionA": "  Dehradun ",
            "optionB": "  Itanagar ",
            "optionC": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "optionD": "  Aizawl ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGovernment of India conducts survey and assessment of forest resources in the country. The organization came into being in June 1981. The headquarters of Forest Survey of India (FSI) are at Dehradun. ",
            "keyString": "848518s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following statements about the Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Grameen Kaushalya Yojana (DDU - GKY) is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  It is a placement - linked skill training programme exclusively for rural girls. ",
            "optionB": "  It aims to convert India's demographic surplus into a demographic dividend. ",
            "optionC": "  The scheme aims to benefit more than 55 million poor rural folk. ",
            "optionD": "  Generational poverty alleviation programme. ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"It is a placement - linked skill training programme exclusively for rural girls\" is an incorrect statement. ",
            "keyString": "848547s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term \"Two - State Solution\" is sometimes mentioned in the news in the context of the affairs of -",
            "optionA": "  China ",
            "optionB": "  Israel ",
            "optionC": "  Iraq ",
            "optionD": "  Yemen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe \"Two - State Solution\" is used in the context of the Israel Palestine issue. It envisages an independent State of Palestine alongside the State of Israel west of the Jordan River. ",
            "keyString": "848561s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the 14th ASEAN - India summit organized?",
            "optionA": "  Vientiane  ",
            "optionB": "  Islamabad ",
            "optionC": "  Dhaka ",
            "optionD": "  Davos ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t14th ASEAN - India Summit and 11th East Asia Summit was organized in Vientiane. ",
            "keyString": "848572s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "United Nations General Assembly declared the year 2013 as -",
            "optionA": "  International Year of Water Cooperation ",
            "optionB": "  International Year of Space Cooperation  ",
            "optionC": "  International Year of Air Cooperation ",
            "optionD": "  International Year of Science and Technology Cooperation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 11 February 2011, the UN General Assembly, decided to proclaim 2013 International Year of Water Cooperation. ",
            "keyString": "848585s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The International Court of Justice is located at :",
            "optionA": "  Geneva ",
            "optionB": "  Hague ",
            "optionC": "  Amsterdam ",
            "optionD": "  Vienna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe International Court of Justice, also known as the World Court, is the main judicial organ of the UN. It was established in June 1945 by the Charter of the United Nations and began work in April 1946. The seat of the Court is at the Peace Palace in the Hague (Netherlands). ",
            "keyString": "882330s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which nation, India has signed an agreement 'Mobilize Your City' in September 2018?",
            "optionA": "  Sweden ",
            "optionB": "  Germany ",
            "optionC": "  Japan ",
            "optionD": "  France ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia and France signed implementation agreement on 'Mobilize Your City'. ",
            "keyString": "882361s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one country is not a permanent member of the Security Council of the United Nations?",
            "optionA": "  France  ",
            "optionB": "  Germany ",
            "optionC": "  Russia  ",
            "optionD": "  USA ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Security Council has five permanent members - China, France, Russia, the United Kingdom, and the United States. ",
            "keyString": "882375s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following is not a member of G-7?",
            "optionA": "  France ",
            "optionB": "  Germany ",
            "optionC": "  Russia ",
            "optionD": "  Japan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Group of Seven (G-7) is an inter - governmental political forum consisting of Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, the United Kingdom and the United States.",
            "keyString": "882388s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the head - office of the World Council of Churches?",
            "optionA": "  Switzerland ",
            "optionB": "  Germany ",
            "optionC": "  France ",
            "optionD": "  Italy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe head - office of the World Council of Churches is in Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "882400s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state organised India's first Tribal Entrepreneurship Summit in November 2017?",
            "optionA": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionC": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionD": "  Odisha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia's first Tribal Entrepreneurship Summit began in Dantewada, a district in the Bastar region of Chhattisgarh on 14 November 2017.",
            "keyString": "950716s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the fifth BRICS Summit hosted by South Africa in March 2013?",
            "optionA": "  Pretoria ",
            "optionB": "  Cape Town ",
            "optionC": "  Durban ",
            "optionD": "  Johannesburg ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSouth Africa hosted the fifth BRICS Summit from 26 to 27 March 2013 at the Durban International Convention Centre. ",
            "keyString": "950744s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not associated with NAFTA?",
            "optionA": "  UK  ",
            "optionB": "  Canada  ",
            "optionC": "  Mexico ",
            "optionD": "  USA ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) is an agreement or treaty signed by Canada, Mexico, and the United States, affective from 1 Jan 1994 for free trade between members. ",
            "keyString": "950757s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India is not a member of which of the following organization?",
            "optionA": "  SAARC ",
            "optionB": "  BRICS ",
            "optionC": "  BIMSTEC ",
            "optionD": "  NATO ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia is not a member of NATO. ",
            "keyString": "950767s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are members of BRICS?",
            "optionA": "  Bhutan, Russia, India, China and Sri Lanka ",
            "optionB": "  Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa ",
            "optionC": "  Brazil, Russia, Indonesia, China and Singapore ",
            "optionD": "  Bangladesh, Republic of Korea, Indonesia, Canada and Sri Lanka ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBrazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa are members of BRICS. ",
            "keyString": "950777s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 2015 G-20 Summit was held at -",
            "optionA": "  Istanbul - Turkey ",
            "optionB": "  Antalya - Turkey ",
            "optionC": "  Ankara - Turkey  ",
            "optionD": "  Izmir - Turkey ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 2015 G-20 Antalya summit was the tenth annual meeting of the G-20 heads of government/heads of state. It was held in Belek, Antalya Province, Turkey on 15 - 16 November 2015. ",
            "keyString": "983011s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Central Food Technology Research Institute situated?",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionC": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "optionD": "  Mysore ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCentral Food Technology Research Institute is situated in Mysore. ",
            "keyString": "983039s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On 8 March 2013 President of India has released commemorative postage stamp on late Sahir Ludhianvi at Rashtrapati Bhawan, Ludhianvi was :",
            "optionA": "  the translator of the Omar Khayyam's Rubaiyat ",
            "optionB": "  an eminent social activist of India ",
            "optionC": "  one of the top Urdu dramatists and actor ",
            "optionD": "  widely acclaimed as a people's poet ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 8 March 2013 President of India has released commemorative postage stamp on late Sahir Ludhianvi at Rashtrapati Bhawan, Ludhianvi was widely acclaimed as a people's poet. ",
            "keyString": "983052s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is not a human rights group?",
            "optionA": "  Greenpeace Movement ",
            "optionB": "  Amnesty International ",
            "optionC": "  PUCL ",
            "optionD": "  PUDR ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGreenpeace uses non-violent creative action to pave the way towards a greener, more peaceful world, and to confront the systems that threaten our environment. ",
            "keyString": "983063s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Development Forum (IDF) was earlier known as :",
            "optionA": "  Aid India Consortium ",
            "optionB": "  Aid India Bank ",
            "optionC": "  World Bank  ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Aid - India Consortium was organized in 1958 as an international scheme to support the economic development of India, and led by the World Bank. This later came to be known as the Indian Development Forum. ",
            "keyString": "983074s33m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements :\nThe India - Africa Summit\n1. Held in 2015 was the third such Summit.\n2. Was actually initiated by Jawaharlal Nehru in 1951.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first India - Africa Summit was held from 4 April to 8 April 2008 in New Delhi, India.",
            "keyString": "16054s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to a grouping of countries known as BRICS, consider the following statements :\n1. The First Summit of BRICS was held in Rio de Janeiro in 2009.\n2. South Africa was the last to join the BRICS grouping.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe First Summit of BRICS was held in Russia. So, statement 1 is false. ",
            "keyString": "16084s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to 'Asia Pacific Ministerial Conference on Housing and Urban Development (APMCHUD)' consider the following statements :\n1. The first APMCHUD was held in India in 2006 on the theme 'Emerging Urban Forms - Policy Responses and Governance Structure'.\n2. India hosts all the Annual Ministerial Conferences in partnership with ADB, APEC and ASEAN.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Asia Pacific Ministerial Conference on Housing and Urban Development (APMCHUD) was established in 2006 to promote sustainable housing and urban development for human settlements in the Asia - Pacific Region. ",
            "keyString": "16099s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to the 'Trans - Pacific Partnership', consider the following statements:\n1. It is an agreement among all the Pacific Rim countries except China and Russia.\n2. It is a strategic alliance for the purpose of maritime security only.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Trans - Pacific Partnership (TPP), or Trans-Pacific Partnership Agreement, was a proposed trade agreement between Australia, Brunei, Canada, Chile, Japan, Malaysia, Mexico, New Zealand, Peru, Singapore, Vietnam, and the United States signed on 4 February 2016. ",
            "keyString": "16111s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to 'Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons (OPCW)', consider the following statements :\n1. It is an organization of European Union in working relation with NATO and WHO.\n2. It monitors chemical industry to prevent new weapons from emerging.\n3. It provides assistance and protection to States (Parties) against chemical weapons threats.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs the implementing body for the Chemical Weapons Convention, the Organization for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons, with its 193 Member States, oversees the global endeavour to permanently and verifiably eliminate chemical weapons. ",
            "keyString": "16124s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the headquarters of World Trade Organisation (WTO)?",
            "optionA": "  New York ",
            "optionB": "  Geneva ",
            "optionC": "  Madrid ",
            "optionD": "  Paris ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of World Trade Organisation (WTO) is located at Geneva, Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "48318s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The international township built near Pondicherry in India in coloration with UNESCO is called -",
            "optionA": "  Elbaville ",
            "optionB": "  Auroville ",
            "optionC": "  Gayaville ",
            "optionD": "  Broadway ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAuroville is an international township built near Pondicherry in India in coloration with UNESCO. ",
            "keyString": "48347s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a cultural organisation?",
            "optionA": "  UNESCO ",
            "optionB": "  ILO ",
            "optionC": "  WHO ",
            "optionD": "  FAO ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUNESCO: United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization. ",
            "keyString": "48360s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The non-permanent members of the Security Council of the UN elected by the General Assembly for two years term at present include (2 year term which begins on the January 1, 2011) -",
            "optionA": "  Japan, India, Hungary, Venezuela ",
            "optionB": "  Morocco, Cape, Verde, Belgium, Russia ",
            "optionC": "  Zimbabwe, Venezuela, India, France ",
            "optionD": "  Colombia, Germany, India, Portugal, South Africa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor the 2 year term which begins on the January 1, 2011, the elected non-permanent members for this 2 year period will be Colombia, Germany, India, Portugal, and South Africa.",
            "keyString": "48370s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following countries is not a member of G-15?",
            "optionA": "  Jamaica ",
            "optionB": "  Indonesia ",
            "optionC": "  Colombia ",
            "optionD": "  Peru ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tColombia is not a member of G-15. ",
            "keyString": "48380s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is used as the logo of the World Wide Fund for Nature (WWF)?",
            "optionA": "  Deer ",
            "optionB": "  Panda ",
            "optionC": "  Camel ",
            "optionD": "  Lion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe giant panda is the symbol of WWF.",
            "keyString": "98643s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following countries is not a member of the G-8 group?",
            "optionA": "  Germany ",
            "optionB": "  France ",
            "optionC": "  Italy ",
            "optionD": "  Spain ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tG-8 group has turned into G-7 after suspension of Russia. Spain is not a member of G-7 among the following. ",
            "keyString": "98672s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pakistan which rejoined the Commonwealth, had pulled itself out of it in the year -",
            "optionA": "  1978 ",
            "optionB": "  1975 ",
            "optionC": "  1972 ",
            "optionD": "  1982 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPakistan which rejoined the Commonwealth, had pulled itself out of it in the year 1972. ",
            "keyString": "98685s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following countries is not a member of SAARC?\n",
            "optionA": "  Nepal ",
            "optionB": "  Bangladesh ",
            "optionC": "  Afghanistan ",
            "optionD": "  Myanmar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:The South Asian Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC) is an organization of South Asian nations, which was established on 8 December 1985 when the government of Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Maldives, Nepal, Pakistan, and Sri Lanka formally adopted its charter providing for the promotion of economic and social progress, cultural development within the South Asia region and also for friendship and cooperation with other developing countries. It has its headquarters in Kathmandu, Nepal. It has total 8 member countries. ",
            "keyString": "98697s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main aim of SAARC is -",
            "optionA": "  Regional Cooperation ",
            "optionB": "  Internal affairs ",
            "optionC": "  Non-alignity ",
            "optionD": "  Peaceful Coexistence ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSAARC aims to promote economic growth, social progress and cultural development within the South Asia region. The objectives of SAARC, as defined in its charter, are as follows : Promote the welfare of the peoples of South Asia and improve their quality of life. ",
            "keyString": "98709s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of principal organs of UNO is -",
            "optionA": "  3 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  5 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main bodies of the United Nations are the General Assembly, the Security Council, the Economic and Social Council, the Trusteeship Council, the International Court of Justice, and the UN Secretariat. ",
            "keyString": "131308s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "G-7 includes -",
            "optionA": "  South Africa ",
            "optionB": "  Australia ",
            "optionC": "  India ",
            "optionD": "  Italy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Group of Seven (G-7) consists of Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Japan, the United Kingdom and the United States. ",
            "keyString": "131336s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "INTERPOL means -",
            "optionA": "  International Political Conference ",
            "optionB": "  International Criminal Police Organisation ",
            "optionC": "  None of these ",
            "optionD": "  International Association of Police Officers ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tINTERPOL means International Criminal Police Organisation. ",
            "keyString": "131349s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of UN is located in -",
            "optionA": "  Rome ",
            "optionB": "  Geneva ",
            "optionC": "  New York ",
            "optionD": "  Washington ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe United Nations is headquartered in New York City in a complex designed by a board of architects led by Wallace Harrison and built by the architectural firm Harrison & Abramovitz. ",
            "keyString": "131360s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The SAARC movement was launched for -",
            "optionA": "  political alliances ",
            "optionB": "  regional cooperation ",
            "optionC": "  cultural exchanges ",
            "optionD": "  military strategy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe SAARC was founded in Dhaka on 8 December 1985. Its secretariat is based in Kathmandu, Nepal. The organization promotes development of economic and regional integration. It launched the South Asian Free Trade Area in 2006.",
            "keyString": "131370s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following countries is not a member of the Nuclear Suppliers Group (NSG)?",
            "optionA": "  France ",
            "optionB": "  Russia ",
            "optionC": "  USA ",
            "optionD": "  Iran ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIran is not a member of the Nuclear Suppliers Group (NSG). ",
            "keyString": "163841s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 11th BRICS Summit in 2019 was hosted by -",
            "optionA": "  China ",
            "optionB": "  Russia ",
            "optionC": "  Brazil ",
            "optionD": "  India ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 11th BRICS Summit in 2019 was hosted by Brazil. ",
            "keyString": "163872s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which country hosted the 9th BRICS Summit in the year 2017?",
            "optionA": "  Brazil ",
            "optionB": "  Russia ",
            "optionC": "  India ",
            "optionD": "  China ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChina hosted the 9th BRICS Summit in 2017. ",
            "keyString": "163888s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following countries is not a member of the BRICS group?",
            "optionA": "  Brazil ",
            "optionB": "  Russia ",
            "optionC": "  China ",
            "optionD": "  Indonesia ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndonesia is not a member of the BRICS group. Brazil, Russia, China, India and South Africa are the members. ",
            "keyString": "163901s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following nations is not a member of the Eurasian Economic Union?",
            "optionA": "  Belarus ",
            "optionB": "  Russia ",
            "optionC": "  Kazakhstan ",
            "optionD": "  Uzbekistan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEurasian Economic Union member states are Armenia, Belarus, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, and Russia. The correct option is D. ",
            "keyString": "163912s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Indian state hosted the 3 day long 'International Yoga Fest' held from 8th to 10th March 2017?",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDelhi hosted the 3 day long 'International Yoga Fest' held from 8th to 10th March 2017. ",
            "keyString": "197135s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Punjab Lalit Kala Academy located?",
            "optionA": "  Muktasar ",
            "optionB": "  Ludhiana ",
            "optionC": "  Patiala ",
            "optionD": "  Chandigarh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Punjab Lalit Kala Academy is Punjab's state academy of fine arts. It is located in Chandigarh. ",
            "keyString": "197165s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the headquarters of the UNESCO?",
            "optionA": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  London ",
            "optionC": "  Paris ",
            "optionD": "  New York ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUNESCO has 195 Members and 8 Associate Members and is governed by the General Conference and the Executive Board.The Organization has more than 50 field offices around the world and its headquarters are located in Paris. ",
            "keyString": "197178s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The International Organization for Standardization (ISO) is located in :",
            "optionA": "  Geneva ",
            "optionB": "  London ",
            "optionC": "  Rome ",
            "optionD": "  Vienna ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe International Organization for Standardization (ISO) was founded in 1947 and is headquartered in Geneva, Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "197189s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the World Economic Forum Meet - 2016, organized?",
            "optionA": "  Switzerland ",
            "optionB": "  Laos ",
            "optionC": "  Austria ",
            "optionD": "  France ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe World Economic Forum Annual Meeting 2016, Mastering the Fourth Industrial Revolution, was held in Davos - Klosters, Switzerland.",
            "keyString": "197199s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is Human Rights Organisation?",
            "optionA": "  The French community ",
            "optionB": "  The Organisation of African Unity ",
            "optionC": "  The Arab League ",
            "optionD": "  Amnesty International ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmnesty International is an international non-governmental organization with its headquarters in the United Kingdom focused on human rights. ",
            "keyString": "229153s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of International Atomic Energy Agency is located in -",
            "optionA": "  Vienna ",
            "optionB": "  London ",
            "optionC": "  Geneva ",
            "optionD": "  Washington ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe International Atomic Energy Agency Secretariat is headquartered at the Vienna International Centre in Vienna, Austria. ",
            "keyString": "229181s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of the International Red Cross is situated in -",
            "optionA": "  Vienna ",
            "optionB": "  Paris ",
            "optionC": "  Hague ",
            "optionD": "  Geneva ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of the International Red Cross is situated in Geneva. ",
            "keyString": "229194s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the first country to withdraw from CENTO?",
            "optionA": "  Iraq ",
            "optionB": "  Afghanistan ",
            "optionC": "  Turkey ",
            "optionD": "  UK ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe new government of Islamic Republic of Iran withdrew the country from CENTO. ",
            "keyString": "229205s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The NAM summit which demanded expansion of the United Nations Security council had met at -",
            "optionA": "  Tehran ",
            "optionB": "  Cairo ",
            "optionC": "  Harare ",
            "optionD": "  Jakarta ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe NAM summit which demanded expansion of the United Nations Security council had met at Jakarta. ",
            "keyString": "279381s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following countries is not a member of a SAARC?",
            "optionA": "  Sri Lanka ",
            "optionB": "  Myanmar ",
            "optionC": "  Maldives ",
            "optionD": "  Bhutan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe South Asian Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC) is the regional intergovernmental organization and geopolitical union of nations in South Asia. Its members include Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Nepal, Maldives, Pakistan and Sri Lanka. ",
            "keyString": "279422s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the first ever Security Council Summit meeting held in early 1992?",
            "optionA": "  New York ",
            "optionB": "  Paris ",
            "optionC": "  Geneva ",
            "optionD": "  London ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 1992 United Nations Security Council election was held on 27 October 1992 during the Forty - seventh session of the United Nations General Assembly, held at United Nations Headquarters in New York City. ",
            "keyString": "279436s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following country is not a member of G-7?",
            "optionA": "  Japan ",
            "optionB": "  Russia ",
            "optionC": "  France ",
            "optionD": "  Italy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRussia is not a member of G-7. ",
            "keyString": "279448s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not an agency of UN?",
            "optionA": "  World Health Organisation ",
            "optionB": "  Food and Agricultural Organisation ",
            "optionC": "  International Committee of the Red Cross ",
            "optionD": "  International Monetary Fund ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInternational Committee of the Red Cross is not an agency of UN. ",
            "keyString": "279459s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did East African Development Bank come into force?",
            "optionA": "  1967 ",
            "optionB": "  1980 ",
            "optionC": "  1982 ",
            "optionD": "  1983 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEast African Development Bank was established in 1967 under the treaty of the then East African Cooperation between Kenya, Tanzania, and Uganda. ",
            "keyString": "322024s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was Bank of Central African States formed?",
            "optionA": "  1974 ",
            "optionB": "  1978 ",
            "optionC": "  1973 ",
            "optionD": "  1979 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "322113s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Nuclear Non - Proliferation Treaty came into force in -",
            "optionA": "  1967 ",
            "optionB": "  1970 ",
            "optionC": "  1971 ",
            "optionD": "  1974 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOpened for signature in 1968, the Nuclear Non - Proliferation Treaty entered into force in 1970. On 11 May 1995, the Treaty was extended indefinitely. A total of 191 States have joined the Treaty, including the five nuclear - weapon States. ",
            "keyString": "322153s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year was the Indian Space Research Organization (ISRO) founded?",
            "optionA": "  1967 ",
            "optionB": "  1969 ",
            "optionC": "  1970 ",
            "optionD": "  1974 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Space Research Organization (ISRO) was founded on 15 August 1969.",
            "keyString": "322183s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year, UN General Assembly terminated South Africa's mandate over Namibia?",
            "optionA": "  1968 ",
            "optionB": "  1966 ",
            "optionC": "  1969 ",
            "optionD": "  1965 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 27 October 1966, the UN General Assembly terminated South Africa's mandate over Namibia, and declared the territory to be the direct responsibility of the UN. ",
            "keyString": "322208s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Bali Ministerial Declaration and the ministerial decisions that were adopted on 7 December 2013 contained several issues. Which of the following are related to the Least - Developed Countries?\n1. Preferential Rules of Origin for Least - Developed Countries.\n2. Operationalized of the Waiver Concerning Preferential Treatment to Services.\n3. Duty - Free and Quota - Free (DFQF) Market Access for Least - Developed Countries.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 only ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "385100s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements regarding the United Nations Peacekeeping Force is/are correct?\n1. The first peacekeeping force was sent to Egypt.\n2. Peacekeeping force is accountable to the Security Council.\n3. First women peacekeeping force was sent by India to Liberia.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 only ",
            "optionC": "  3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA United Nations peacekeeping mission has three power centers. The first is the Special Representative of the Secretary - General, the official leader of the mission. This person is responsible for all political and diplomatic activity, overseeing relations with both the parties to the peace treaty and the UN member - states in general. They are often a senior member of the Secretariat.",
            "keyString": "385133s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following statements about the Trans - Pacific Partnership (TPP) is/are correct?\n1. The TPP was signed by 12 Pacific Rim Nations in the year 2015.\n2. The TPP is likely to be a game - changer in global trade as member countries account for about 40% of global GDP.\n3. India is a founder member of TPP.\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below.",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 only ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1 only ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Trans - Pacific Partnership (TPP), or Trans - Pacific Partnership Agreement, was a proposed trade agreement between Australia, Brunei, Canada, Chile, Japan, Malaysia, Mexico, New Zealand, Peru, Singapore, Vietnam, and the United States signed on 4 February 2016.",
            "keyString": "385151s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was South Sudan admitted to UN as the 193rd member country of UN?",
            "optionA": "  2006 ",
            "optionB": "  2011 ",
            "optionC": "  2000 ",
            "optionD": "  2002 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSouth Sudan was admitted to UN as the 193rd member country of UN on 13 July 2011. ",
            "keyString": "385167s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was Common Market for Eastern and Southern African (COMESA) formed?",
            "optionA": "  1995 ",
            "optionB": "  1994 ",
            "optionC": "  1992 ",
            "optionD": "  1991 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Common Market for Eastern and Southern Africa is a free trade area with twenty - one member states stretching from Tunisia to Eswatini. COMESA was formed in December 1994, replacing a Preferential Trade Area which had existed since 1981.",
            "keyString": "385179s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the committee that has been constituted by the union government to examine the existing framework with regard to virtual currencies?",
            "optionA": "  Dharamraj Committee ",
            "optionB": "  Dinesh Sharma Committee ",
            "optionC": "  Dheeraj Sharma Committee ",
            "optionD": "  Govind Rajan Committee ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Union Government constituted an Inter - Disciplinary Committee to examine the existing framework with regard to Virtual Currencies. The committee is headed by Dinesh Sharma. ",
            "keyString": "420579s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following cities hosted the 3rd World Trauma Congress recently?",
            "optionA": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Dacca ",
            "optionC": "  Singapore ",
            "optionD": "  Bangkok ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNew Delhi hosted 3rd World Trauma Congress. The 3rd World Congress was a call to action to all stakeholders to end all deaths due to trauma. ",
            "keyString": "420608s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which country has been admitted in July 2013 as the 28th member of the European Union?",
            "optionA": "  Bulgaria ",
            "optionB": "  Croatia ",
            "optionC": "  Cyprus ",
            "optionD": "  Romania ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 9 December 2011 leaders from the European Union and Croatia signed the accession treaty. The country became the 28th European Union member country on 1 July 2013. ",
            "keyString": "420621s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which organisation has the NITI Aayog signed a Memorandum of Understanding on Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) and entered into a three - year partnership?",
            "optionA": "  FICCI ",
            "optionB": "  CII ",
            "optionC": "  QCI ",
            "optionD": "  ASSOCHAM ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe NITI Aayog and the Confederation of Indian Industry (CII) on 8 August 2018, signed a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) on Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) and entered into a three - year partnership. ",
            "keyString": "420633s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following event is not correctly matched with the year in which it happened?",
            "optionA": "  Inauguration of the SWIFT system of electronic interbank fund transfers worldwide - 1985 ",
            "optionB": "  Conclusion of the Uruguay Round of GATT - 1994 ",
            "optionC": "  Inauguration of the World Trade Organization - 1995 ",
            "optionD": "  Establishment of the first wholly electronic stock exchange (Nasdaq) - 1971 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInauguration of the SWIFT system of electronic interbank fund transfers worldwide was done in 1973 and not in 1985. ",
            "keyString": "420644s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many are the non - permanent members of United Nations Security Council?",
            "optionA": "  Five ",
            "optionB": "  Ten ",
            "optionC": "  Fifteen ",
            "optionD": "  Twenty ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMembership of the United Nations Security Council is held by the five permanent members and ten elected, non - permanent members.",
            "keyString": "452879s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which African countries are the members of the East African Development Bank :",
            "optionA": "  Kenya ",
            "optionB": "  Tanzania ",
            "optionC": "  Uganda ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 13 countries members of the East African Development Bank are Burundi, Comoros, Djibouti, Ethiopia, Eritrea, Kenya, Rwanda, Seychelles, Somalia, South Sudan, Sudan, Tanzania, and Uganda.",
            "keyString": "452907s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of World Trade Organisation (WTO) are located in :",
            "optionA": "  France ",
            "optionB": "  Switzerland ",
            "optionC": "  USA ",
            "optionD": "  England ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of World Trade Organisation (WTO) are located in Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "452920s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first summit of the Forum for India - Pacific Islands Cooperation (FIPIC) was held in :",
            "optionA": "  Jaipur ",
            "optionB": "  Suva ",
            "optionC": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Port Moresby ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe inaugural FIPIC summit, at the level of Heads of Government was held in Suva, Fiji. ",
            "keyString": "452931s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following country is the new member of International Coffee Organisation?",
            "optionA": "  India ",
            "optionB": "  Sri Lanka ",
            "optionC": "  Kenya ",
            "optionD": "  Vietnam ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVietnam is the new member of International Coffee Organisation. ",
            "keyString": "452941s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whose part is the International Bureau of Education :",
            "optionA": "  UNESCO ",
            "optionB": "  UNIDO ",
            "optionC": "  IMF ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe International Bureau of Education is a UNESCO category 1 institute mandated as the Centre of Excellence in curriculum and related matters. ",
            "keyString": "486460s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following was the theme of the \"International Day of United Nations Peacekeepers\" for the year 2015?",
            "optionA": "  Peacekeeping is a Global Partnership ",
            "optionB": "  UN70 and UN Peacekeeping : Past, Present and Future ",
            "optionC": "  Women in Peacekeeping  ",
            "optionD": "  A force for the future ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "486488s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the headquarters of the Universal Postal Union?",
            "optionA": "  Switzerland ",
            "optionB": "  UK ",
            "optionC": "  Iran ",
            "optionD": "  India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of the Universal Postal Union is in Bern, Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "486501s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Seventh BRICS Summit is proposed to be held in 2015 at -",
            "optionA": "  Durban, South Africa ",
            "optionB": "  Ufa, Russia ",
            "optionC": "  New Delhi, India ",
            "optionD": "  Sanya, China ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Seventh Summit of the BRICS was held from 9 - 10 July 2015, in Ufa, the Russian Federation. ",
            "keyString": "486512s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Angola, Malaysia, New Zealand, Spain and Venezuela were elected as non-permanent members on 16th October 2014 to serve in -",
            "optionA": "  The UN General Assembly ",
            "optionB": "  The UN Trusteeship Council ",
            "optionC": "  The UN Human Rights Commission ",
            "optionD": "  The UN Security Council ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAngola, Malaysia, New Zealand, Spain and Venezuela were elected as non-permanent members on 16th October 2014 to serve in the UN Security Council. ",
            "keyString": "486522s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was SAARC founded?",
            "optionA": "  1982 ",
            "optionB": "  1984 ",
            "optionC": "  1985 ",
            "optionD": "  1983 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSAARC was founded on 8 December 1985, Dhaka, Bangladesh.",
            "keyString": "536456s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a member of G-15?",
            "optionA": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionB": "  Malaysia ",
            "optionC": "  Indonesia ",
            "optionD": "  India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPakistan is not a member of G-15. ",
            "keyString": "536484s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amnesty International has its headquarters at -",
            "optionA": "  Berlin ",
            "optionB": "  New York ",
            "optionC": "  Washington ",
            "optionD": "  London ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmnesty International (also referred to as Amnesty or AI) is an international non-governmental organization with its headquarters in the United Kingdom (London) focused on human rights. ",
            "keyString": "536497s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Headquarters of the World Health Organisation is located at -",
            "optionA": "  Geneva ",
            "optionB": "  Washington ",
            "optionC": "  New York ",
            "optionD": "  Rome ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHeadquarters of the World Health Organisation is located at Geneva, Switzerland. ",
            "keyString": "536508s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The working language(s) of the UNESCO is/are -",
            "optionA": "  French only ",
            "optionB": "  English only ",
            "optionC": "  English and French ",
            "optionD": "  English, French and Russian ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe six official languages of UNESCO are Arabic, Chinese, English, French, Russian and Spanish. ",
            "keyString": "536518s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the SAARC countries the most densely populated country is?",
            "optionA": "  Bangladesh  ",
            "optionB": "  India ",
            "optionC": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionD": "  Maldives ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmong the SAARC countries, the most densely populated country is Bangladesh. ",
            "keyString": "568650s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following parties won the most number of seats in the Punjab Legislative Election 2017?",
            "optionA": "  Bharatiya Janata Party ",
            "optionB": "  Indian National Congress ",
            "optionC": "  Aam Aadmi Party ",
            "optionD": "  Shiromani Akalidal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian National Congress won the most number of seats in the Punjab Legislative Election 2017. ",
            "keyString": "568679s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an example of Cartel?",
            "optionA": "  OPEC ",
            "optionB": "  IMF ",
            "optionC": "  WTO ",
            "optionD": "  UNO ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Organization of Petroleum \u2010 Exporting Countries (OPEC) is perhaps the best \u2010 known example of an international cartel; OPEC members meet regularly to decide how much oil each member of the cartel will be allowed to produce. ",
            "keyString": "568691s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a World Bank group of five institutions?",
            "optionA": "  IMF ",
            "optionB": "  IDA ",
            "optionC": "  ILO ",
            "optionD": "  ITU ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInternational Development Association (IDA) ",
            "keyString": "568703s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of the following is also called as World Bank -",
            "optionA": "  IMF ",
            "optionB": "  IBRD ",
            "optionC": "  WTO ",
            "optionD": "  IDA ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe world bank is also known as International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD). ",
            "keyString": "568714s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Earth summit was held at :",
            "optionA": "  Buenos Aires ",
            "optionB": "  Rio De Janeiro ",
            "optionC": "  Dar-es-Salam ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1992, more than 100 heads of state met in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil for the first international Earth Summit convened to address urgent problems of environmental protection and socio - economic development. ",
            "keyString": "602076s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following was a major decision taken at the fifth BRICS summit?",
            "optionA": "  Establishment of a new development bank ",
            "optionB": "  Reformation of the United Nations ",
            "optionC": "  Common military exercise ",
            "optionD": "  Cultural exchange among the BRICS countries ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEstablishment of a new development bank was a major decision taken at the fifth BRICS summit. ",
            "keyString": "602105s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 2017, which state government launched the 'Vision - 2025' project to seek public opinion for their dream state?",
            "optionA": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Odisha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Karnataka Government launched 'Vision-2025' project across the state with an aim to draft policy for the development of the state in next seven years by seeking the opinion of the public. ",
            "keyString": "602117s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Electrification prior to the launch of 'Saubhagya Scheme'. Which one of the following is not among them?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEight States which have already achieved more than 99 percent household electrification prior to launch of Saubhagya scheme are ineligible for participation under the award scheme. These eight states are Andhra Pradesh, Gujarat, Goa, Haryana, Himachal Pradesh, Kerala, Punjab and Tamil Nadu.",
            "keyString": "602128s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amnesty International is an organization which is associated with -",
            "optionA": "  Protection of women's right  ",
            "optionB": "  Protection of human rights ",
            "optionC": "  Abolition of untouchability ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmnesty International (AI), international nongovernmental organization (NGO) founded in London on 28 May 1961, that seeks to publicize violations by governments and other entities of rights recognized in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights (1948), especially freedom of speech and of conscience and the right against torture. ",
            "keyString": "602139s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which mela/fair to be listed in UNESCO's list of intangible cultural heritage?",
            "optionA": "  Kumbh Mela ",
            "optionB": "  Gangasagar Mela ",
            "optionC": "  Jagannath Rath - Yatra Mela ",
            "optionD": "  Pushkar Fair ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to a report released by the Ministry of External Affairs, the Kumbh Mela has been inscribed on the Representative List of Intangible Cultural Heritage of Humanity by the Intergovernmental Committee for the Safeguarding of the Intangible Cultural Heritage under UNESCO. ",
            "keyString": "634762s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India is not a member of :",
            "optionA": "  G-20 ",
            "optionB": "  G-8 ",
            "optionC": "  SAARC ",
            "optionD": "  UN ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia is not a member of G-8. ",
            "keyString": "634789s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The BRICS New Development Bank (NDB) has been set up for",
            "optionA": "  Funding Infrastructure projects in emerging economics for sustainable development ",
            "optionB": "  Funding non - infrastructure projects in emerging economics for sustainable development ",
            "optionC": "  Funding infrastructure projects in developed countries ",
            "optionD": "  Funding infrastructural projects in BRICS countries only ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe New Development Bank (NDB), formerly referred to as the BRICS Development Bank, is a multilateral development bank established by the BRICS states (Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa). According to the Agreement on the NDB, \"the Bank shall support public or private projects through loans, guarantees, equity participation and other financial instruments.\" ",
            "keyString": "634802s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Official language of African Development Bank -",
            "optionA": "  English ",
            "optionB": "  French ",
            "optionC": "  A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe African Development Bank multicultural status is displayed through the use of two official languages, English and French. ",
            "keyString": "634813s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the official language of the 'Common Market' for Eastern and Southern Africa?",
            "optionA": "  English ",
            "optionB": "  French ",
            "optionC": "  Portuguese ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe official language of the 'Common Market' for Eastern and Southern Africa is English, French and Portuguese. ",
            "keyString": "634823s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In April 2013, an agreement was signed between India and a country which extends the use of training and exercise facilities in India to the army of that country for a further period of five years from August, 2013. Sort out the country from among the following :",
            "optionA": "  Malaysia ",
            "optionB": "  Singapore ",
            "optionC": "  Myanmar ",
            "optionD": "  Bangladesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "703022s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a member of  'Gulf Cooperation Council'?",
            "optionA": "  Iran ",
            "optionB": "  Saudi Arabia ",
            "optionC": "  Oman ",
            "optionD": "  Kuwait ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIran is not a member of 'Gulf Cooperation Council'. ",
            "keyString": "703050s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first BRICS Summit, after the inclusion of South Africa, was held at",
            "optionA": "  Brasilia ",
            "optionB": "  Sanya ",
            "optionC": "  Yekaterinburg ",
            "optionD": "  Durban ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first BRICS Summit, after the inclusion of South Africa, was held at Sanya. ",
            "keyString": "703063s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the context of which of the following do you sometimes find the terms 'amber box, blue box and green box' in the news?",
            "optionA": "  WTO affairs ",
            "optionB": "  SAARC affairs ",
            "optionC": "  UNFCCC affairs ",
            "optionD": "  India - EU negotiations on FTA ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn WTO terminology, subsidies in general are identified by 'Boxes' which are given the colours of traffic lights : green (permitted), amber (slow down - i.e. be reduced), red (forbidden). ",
            "keyString": "703074s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The BRICS Bank has its headquarters in?",
            "optionA": "  India ",
            "optionB": "  Russia ",
            "optionC": "  China ",
            "optionD": "  South Africa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe BRICS Bank has its headquarters in Shanghai, China. ",
            "keyString": "703085s34m4h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}